<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Takri</title>
  <subtitle>Thoughts, stories and ideas.</subtitle>
  <link href="http://localhost:8080/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://localhost:8080"/>
  <updated>2021-05-19T13:12:03.000+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:8080/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Rahul Gajjar</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>About Takri</title>
    <link href="http://localhost:8080/about-takri/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-19T13:12:03.000+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://localhost:8080/about-takri/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The origin of the name Takri is uncertain. It is also known as Takari, Takkari, Tankri, etc. It is also believed that it comes from the old landed class of Punjab called Takka, or that it is a script of Takkas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:2368/content/images/2021/05/TakriRegion.jpg&quot; class=&quot;kg-image&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;660&quot; height=&quot;747&quot; srcset=&quot;http://localhost:2368/content/images/size/w600/2021/05/TakriRegion.jpg 600w, http://localhost:2368/content/images/2021/05/TakriRegion.jpg 660w&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Historical geographic distribution of Takri. Reference from Proposal to Encode the Takri Script&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Takri alphabets are related to Sharda and Gurmukhi alphabets. It is descended from the Devāśeṣa alphabet, which developed from the Sharada alphabet. The Takri script was in use between the 16th and 19th centuries. It was mainly used in the region now known as  Jammu, Himachal Pradesh, Pahari region of Punjab, and Uttarakhand. Different variations of Takri script were used to write different languages like Chambeali, Dogri, and other Pahari languages.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Takri is written from left to right using thirty-four consonant letters, ten vowel letters, and ten vowel diacritics. It is an abugida. (abugida means without the use of vowel signs) It uses dynamic letters which are written depending on the form of the consonant. Each consonant carries an inherent ‘a’ vowel. A vowel sign is attached to change the inherent vowel. Other vowels are written with one of the vowel diacritics unless they appear at the beginning of a word. In that case, they are written using one of the independent vowel letters. The script structure is much like Devanagari. Since Takri fell out of use, people use Devanagari to write languages like Chambeali or Dogri. One notable feature of Takri is that most of its variants do not use headstroke.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Takri has a significant variation in style, it was used in the wide mountainous area and prone to many regional variants developed in isolated mountain communities. That is the main reason why it has significant variations in style. The communities standardized the form of the script which they themselves used but there was no universally applicable standardized variety. However, despite variations in the shapes of letters and the styles of writing, each form was recognized by its users to be Takri, and each variety exhibited certain common features.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
